The stars that burn brightest burn quickest
James Dean is a drama, tv movie film directed by Mark Rydell.
The man behind the legend and a knowing look at 1950s Hollywood are revealed in this dynamic biopic of the meteoric star
whose troubled life echoed his gut-grabbing performances in East of Eden, Rebel Without a Cause and Giant.
James Dean, played by James Franco.
Winton Dean, played by Michael Moriarty.
Pier Angeli, played by Valentina Cervi.
Elia Kazan, played by Enrico Colantoni.
Raymond Massey, played by Edward Herrmann.
Hedda Hopper, played by Joanne Linville.
James Dean is a 2001 American made-for-television biographical drama
film based on the life of the American actor James Dean.
James Franco plays the title role under the direction of Mark Rydell, who chronicles Dean's
rise from a struggling actor to an A-list movie star in 1950s Hollywood.
The film's supporting roles included Michael Moriarty, Valentina
Cervi, Enrico Colantoni, and Edward Herrmann.
The biopic began development at Warner Bros.
in the early 1990s.
At one point, Michael Mann was contracted to direct with
Leonardo DiCaprio starring in the lead role.
After Mann's departure, Des McAnuff, Dennis Hopper, and Milčo
Mančevski were considered for the director's chair.
Rydell was hired as director in 1996, but the film
continued to languish in development hell.
Warner Bros.
then decided to produce James Dean as a TV movie for Turner
Network Television (TNT); both Warner Bros.
and TNT were owned by Time Warner.
Franco was cast as Dean in May 2000 after a search
that resulted in 500 auditions.
Franco researched his role to closely portray Dean.
James Dean was shown on TNT in the United States on August 5, 2001, receiving generally
positive reviews from critics and widespread acclaim for Franco's performance.
The film explores themes of musician, icon, biography, hollywood, dying young.
The tone is emotional.